<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cloud Computing on HEIG-Cloud blog</title>
    <link>http://heig-cloud.github.io/tags/cloud-computing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cloud Computing on HEIG-Cloud blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://heig-cloud.github.io/tags/cloud-computing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How to deploy OpenStack</title>
      <link>http://heig-cloud.github.io/article/2015-12-15%20openstack_deployment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://heig-cloud.github.io/article/2015-12-15%20openstack_deployment/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-deploy-openstack:6edb1a0cfe65e6967cfa8690bfb1a8f5&#34;&gt;How to deploy OpenStack&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deploying OpenStack, or any cloud middleware for that matter, is no
piece of cake. OpenStack consists of many many moving parts that need
to be carefully configured to work correctly. (To give you an idea of
the number of components and their interrelations we have reproduced
below the diagram of the logical architecture from the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.openstack.org/admin-guide-cloud/common/get_started_logical_architecture.html&#34;&gt;official OpenStack documentation&lt;/a&gt;.)
On top of that each cloud deployment is different: different number of
servers to deploy on, different network topologies, different
integration points with existing sytesm, and so on. The complexity of
the configuration far exceeds the capabilities of regular Linux
package managers like APT and YUM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://heig-cloud.github.io/static/img/2015-12-15 openstack_deployment/openstack-arch-kilo-logical-v1.png&#34; alt=&#34;OpenStack Kilo logical architecture&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is it possible to tame this complexity? One has to decide between
two main approaches to installing OpenStack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install manually by following the 150+ page
&lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.openstack.org/kilo/install-guide/install/apt/content/&#34;&gt;OpenStack Installation Guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use a configuration management tool like Puppet, Chef or Ansible and
use ready-made scripts to automate the installation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manual install will be a lot of work. There is a non-negligible
risk of making errors. The installation effort needs to be repated for
every machine. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you want to dedicate ten servers to the
compute component that provides virtual machines. You would have to
repeat ten times the installation of the compute component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The automated install reduces the chances of making errors as you are
relying on scripts developed and tested by somebody else. Repeating
the installation, once it is working, on nine more machines is a
breeze. However a considerable manual effort is still needed to
customize the deployment scripts to your particular situation. To be
able to do that, and to be able to troubleshoot any installation
problems that are likely to occur, you need to become familiar with
the configuration management tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it worth learning a configuration management tool? We think in the
case of OpenStack, the answer is yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the most widely used configuration management tools
&lt;a href=&#34;http://ansible.com&#34;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt; is the least complex one. It is
relatively easy to learn. It is also easyer to deploy as the
competition, as it does not need the setup of a central
server. Instead configuration scripts are pushed from your local
workstation to the machines that need to be configured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RackSpace, one of the bigger cloud service providers, has developed an
OpenStack deployment solution based on Ansible that is now officialy
part of the OpenStack project:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/openstack/openstack-ansible&#34;&gt;openstack-ansible&lt;/a&gt;. This
is our starting base to create a private cloud at HEIG-VD. More on
that in an upcoming blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating your own private cloud</title>
      <link>http://heig-cloud.github.io/article/2015-12-14%20private_cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://heig-cloud.github.io/article/2015-12-14%20private_cloud/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-your-own-private-cloud:365f7f745395937a012ca0f9a668a231&#34;&gt;Creating your own private cloud&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why Cloud Computing has been such a success is that
it &lt;em&gt;automates&lt;/em&gt; many tasks that previously had to be done manually by
system administrators. Take the provisioning of a server to run a web
application. Traditionally this takes several weeks (ordering,
delivering, installing, configuring, &amp;hellip;) while a virtual machine in
the cloud is provisioned with a few clicks and available in two
minutes. This automation, coupled with economies of scale through
immense data centers, is what allows companies like Amazon or
Microsoft to offer cloud services at very low cost. Much cheaper than
what a typical company pays to run its own traditional IT
infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there are many companies that shy away from public cloud offerings
like AWS and Azure because the data they work with is &lt;em&gt;sensitive&lt;/em&gt;. Think
of banks, anybody providing health services like hospitals, or even
schools that need to keep personal data which is protected by privacy
laws. Sometimes using public cloud services has to be ruled out
because there are not enough assurances that the data will be kept
safe. In these cases one can still reap the benefits of cloud
automation by running a &lt;em&gt;private cloud&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To run a private cloud one needs the servers and the cloud
software. For the latter, there basically two options: commercial
software or Open Source
software. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vmware.com/cloud-computing/overview&#34;&gt;VMware&lt;/a&gt;
dominates the commercial cloud segment. Its software is seen as very
solid, well documented, but also quite pricey. In the Open Source
segment two projects dominate: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.openstack.org&#34;&gt;OpenStack&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloudstack.apache.org&#34;&gt;Apache CloudStack&lt;/a&gt;. OpenStack is
very widely used, offers a wide range of functionalities, but has a
(deserved)
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ask.openstack.org/en/question/58965/have-you-ever-experienced-anything-worse-than-openstack/&#34;&gt;reputation to be difficult to install and run&lt;/a&gt;. CloudStack
is
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.getfilecloud.com/blog/2014/02/a-game-of-stacks-openstack-vs-cloudstack/#.VtWc58e75OM&#34;&gt;easier to use&lt;/a&gt;,
but focuses on the core IaaS services: compute, storage and
networking. OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s scope is broader and it offers more
flexibility. Uptake of CloudStack is less than OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We at HEIG-VD have deployed a private cloud for research and teaching
based on OpenStack. In upcoming blog postings we will talk about our
experiences, good and bad, with OpenStack.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>