<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Public Cloud on HEIG-Cloud blog</title>
    <link>http://heig-cloud.github.io/tags/public-cloud/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Public Cloud on HEIG-Cloud blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://heig-cloud.github.io/tags/public-cloud/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating your own private cloud</title>
      <link>http://heig-cloud.github.io/article/2015-12-14%20private_cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://heig-cloud.github.io/article/2015-12-14%20private_cloud/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-your-own-private-cloud:365f7f745395937a012ca0f9a668a231&#34;&gt;Creating your own private cloud&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why Cloud Computing has been such a success is that
it &lt;em&gt;automates&lt;/em&gt; many tasks that previously had to be done manually by
system administrators. Take the provisioning of a server to run a web
application. Traditionally this takes several weeks (ordering,
delivering, installing, configuring, &amp;hellip;) while a virtual machine in
the cloud is provisioned with a few clicks and available in two
minutes. This automation, coupled with economies of scale through
immense data centers, is what allows companies like Amazon or
Microsoft to offer cloud services at very low cost. Much cheaper than
what a typical company pays to run its own traditional IT
infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there are many companies that shy away from public cloud offerings
like AWS and Azure because the data they work with is sensitive. Think
of banks, anybody providing health services like hospitals, or even
schools that need to keep personal data which is protected by privacy
laws. Sometimes using public cloud services has to be ruled out
because there are not enough assurances that the data will be kept
safe. In these cases one can still reap the benefits of cloud
automation by running a &lt;em&gt;private cloud&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To run a private cloud one needs the servers and the cloud
software. For the latter, there basically two options: commercial
software or Open Source
software. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vmware.com/cloud-computing/overview&#34;&gt;VMware&lt;/a&gt;
dominates the commercial cloud segment. Its software is seen as very
solid, well documented, but also quite pricey. In the Open Source
segment two projects dominate: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.openstack.org&#34;&gt;OpenStack&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloudstack.apache.org&#34;&gt;Apache CloudStack&lt;/a&gt;. OpenStack is
very widely used, offers a wide range of functionalities, but has a
(deserved)
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ask.openstack.org/en/question/58965/have-you-ever-experienced-anything-worse-than-openstack/&#34;&gt;reputation to be difficult to install and run&lt;/a&gt;. CloudStack
is
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.getfilecloud.com/blog/2014/02/a-game-of-stacks-openstack-vs-cloudstack/#.VtWc58e75OM&#34;&gt;easier to use&lt;/a&gt;,
but focuses on the core IaaS services: compute, storage and
networking. OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s scope is broader and it offers more
flexibility. Uptake of CloudStack is less than OpenStack&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We at HEIG-VD have deployed a private cloud for research and teaching
based on OpenStack. In upcoming blog postings we will talk about our
experiences, good and bad, with OpenStack.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>